"Your sheep
now become
so great devourers and so wild,
that they eat up, and swallow down
the very men themselves".
Thomas More, "Utopia", 1516
THE SETTLERS
I'm good! I'm good!
It's nothing, it's nothing!
Go back to work!
It's just an arm!
It's just an arm...
In this place, a man without an arm
is one man less, you understand?
I need two men
to bury this body. You and you!
Back to work!
THE KING OF THE WHITE GOLD
Sir?
Good evening, Lieutenant.
Good evening, Don José.
How are things going here?
How are the fences coming?
We lost another man today.
One man less is not a problem.
The Indians are the problem.
In Porvenir, they cut the fences
and ate all my animals.
All my sheep.
Like beasts.
Like the beasts they are.
I want you to find a route
to the Atlantic for my sheep.
A safe and quick route,
Lieutenant.
For this, you will have
to clean this island.
But I need proof.
I will need one man.
- Just one?
- Yes, sir.
Fire!
Another one!
You!
There!
Fire!
Another one!
You!
Fire!
Another one!
You!
Fire!
This is your man?
Yes.
He is a local expert.
He will make a decent guide,
he is good with the rifle.
Look at him,
and look at him.
This is Bill.
I brought him from Mexico.
They say he can smell an Indian
from miles away.
He will go with you
on your mission.
If you say so...
You will thank me.
I wish you a good journey.
We do things differently,
Lieutenant.
Such as?
Look at this enormous land.
Three men!
Doesn't it seem absurd?
No, it doesn't.
Ain't a lieutenant supposed
to have his own unit?
When there is discipline,
one good man is worth more
than ten badly trained.
Well, I don't know Chileans,
but I know others like him.
Like him?
Half Indian, half white.
And what about them?
You never know
who they are going to shoot.
There are many things said about you.
But I haven't seen anything yet.
Yeah, well...
They ain't say
a damn thing about you!
On a trip like this, you are
supposed to eat meat, not fish.
When you ain't got cow, we best
be eating one of those big birds.
You ever had ostrich meat,
Lieutenant?
Yes, I have.
It is almost like cow.
Eat up.
You'd be doing us a favor
if you eat that mess right there too.
In Texas we never eat
where we sleep.
Why is that?
'Cause it is dangerous.
We shouldn't be leaving traces.
What are you afraid of, Bill?
I ain't afraid.
It ain't fear, you hear me?
It is respect.
Them Indians...
Them Comanche...
They are real good trackers.
And you have no idea
how much they dislike
outsiders roaming their lands.
These aren't their lands.
They belong to Menéndez.
Indians don't know nothing
about property, do they?
Ain't that right, boy?
There are things you learn.
In Chiloé,
priests teach the natives
about God.
They teach them not to steal,
to respect your fellow man.
The problem
is when they don't want to learn,
when they have their own god.
Who the fuck was talking to you?
I think he's saying we should have
brought one of them priests.
It would save ourselves some work.
No time for priests.
Me and God,
we already have an understanding.
Good morning, soldier.
I need to speak with your superior.
Captain Ambrosio at your service.
Excuse me, Captain.
Who are you?
Alexander MacLennan.
I work for Mr. Menéndez.
And your clothes?
I served the English Army
during the war.
Allow me to welcome you
to the Republic of Argentina.
Argentina?
Yes.
We are standing right now
on the Andes Mountains.
The Andes?
Yes, the Andes.
I always thought it would be larger.
It is the largest!
Come over here.
Nice and straight!
There! No, no.
This way. Straight.
There should be a right angle
between the ground and the pole.
It is bent, it must go this way.
Look at me!
Like this!
The angle of the pole is bent, sir.
Lift it right here.
Move it in this direction.
But without moving the pole!
And you, what do you do here?
See those two men over there?
Yes.
Our mission
is to accompany Mr. Moreno.
He is in charge
of ratifying the limits
of the Chilean and Argentine border.
It is peaceful out here.
Yes, quite.
Some days I just want to shoot.
Shoot what?
Them, for example.
I don't think
any of your men has an aim
as good as this Chilean's.
You haven't met Vargas.
Let's make it very clear.
Vargas shoots for our team.
That Chilean shoots for yours.
Go ahead, Chilean!
Fire!
Vargas!
Go, my Vargas!
Go ahead!
Fire!
How about a strength competition?
How is your American
at arm wrestling?
Can you feel that, Argentina?
Can you feel that? That's the force!
Get on with it, Bill!
Come on,
your reputation precedes you!
Get on with it,
you're dealing with a real man now!
Hit, hit!
Come on!
Fuck you!
Go!
Go Argentina, damn it!
Who invented this cunt's reputation?
Know how to fight?
What?
Boxing?
Love it!
Stay down, boy! Stay down!
He's all yours now!
That's right, fuck him up!
Hit him again!
Take him out, Lieutenant!
Get off me!
Get the fuck off me!
Little Englishman!
Bravo, Englishman!
Bravo!
Can't see anything.
Let's go.
Good evening, gentlemen.
Good evening, Moreno.
I see you are hurt, Captain.
You should be more careful.
We have visitors.
My name is Alexander MacLennan,
I work for José Menéndez.
José Menéndez...
Do you know,
Mr. MacLennan,
how much land
gave the state of Chile
to your José Menéndez?
Are you aware of that?
How long have you gentlemen
been traveling?
Three days.
Three days of land!
It's quite odd, isn't it?
What is?
Both sides of the border
belonging to the same man...
What I find odd is that men
would fight over a land
where there is fucking nothing.
Mr. MacLennan,
take a look at these people.
Come.
Take a look at their skull.
How particular it is,
how delicate.
These people, Mr. MacLennan,
should be taken to the University,
to Oxford,
to make them engineers or lawyers.
That's what a country
needs to do with its money.
Not fencing for the sheep.
Right, Captain?
What will our visitors think?
One scientist and twenty military.
Bored military.
Nothing good happens
when military get bored.
With your permission.
Come with me, Little Jimmy.
Come with me.
You can't even talk to them.
They come here
with their silk scarves
and their twisted ways.
They trace a line on the ground
and they think they own the world.
Do you know where
we can find more people
who look like that?
Indians?
Yes.
They are not far away.
You need to head west
and go through the forest.
THE HALF-BLOOD
Boy!
Where are you from?
From Chiloé.
And where is that?
Up north.
It's an island.
Same as me.
You know,
sailors
and cowboys...
we're not the same thing,
not the same animal.
What will you do
with your money, Segundo?
I want a horse.
A horse?
What would a half-breed like you
do with a horse?
Once...
in the war...
I had to kill my horse.
Between ten men…
we ate the horse.
Shit, what the hell
is wrong with you?
A man who rides
never eats his horse.
It is like eating a friend,
God damn it!
No one is asking
for your opinion, redneck!
And when I'm in charge,
I don't question what is necessary.
Coming through, Red Pig.
Crazy fucking Brit...
- You stupid son of a bitch!
- Steady, Bill.
You lecture me about discipline
and then you pull shit like that?
You're doing everything wrong,
Lieutenant.
Ever since you brought
that fucking half-breed along.
Horses were awful jittery
last night, Lieutenant.
They woke me up several times.
Strange thing was,
when I woke up he wasn't there.
How is that?
He just wasn't.
I told you
we couldn't trust him.
You're white and he's not.
Our differences
are set in stone.
Easy!
Lieutenant.
How many are there?
More than ten.
Less than twenty.
What do we do?
I reckon they ain't any tougher
than the Apache.
You know about these things.
Tell us what to do.
I just need you to cover me.
We are going to come in
soft and silent like the wind.
Less of the poetry, Bill.
Alright, let's not waste
any more time then.
We attack at dawn.
Alright.
- Check your ammunition.
- It is checked.
I suggest we approach on foot.
We should put the horses
somewhere a little more discreet.
He could stay with the horses...
Don't worry about him,
he is my responsibility.
Stand up! Come here!
Segundo! Come here!
Here!
Alright.
My turn.
Are you alright?
Yes.
How many did you kill?
I don't know.
And you?
Many.
Well, that was way beneath
my expectations.
Your turn.
No, thank you.
The woman...
She's waiting for you.
I'm good here.
Stand up and go now!
Look at me.
Yes...
You think you're better than me
with your judging eyes, watching me?
I see you watching me
and everything I fucking do.
And I do not like it.
If I tell you what to do, you do it!
You understand me?
I see you fucking watching me!
You watch me one more time,
I'll extinguish your fucking flame.
You're destined for darkness,
for blackness,
for fucking nada!
These!
You fucking use them
for a fucking mujer.
When I tell you
there's a woman in there
you go in there and fucking use them,
you understand me?
You disobey me one more time,
I'll extinguish your fucking flame
as easy as a fire with fucking water!
And when I tell you to breathe,
you breathe.
Now go fuck her.
Go and fuck her now.
THE ENDS OF THE EARTH
No way to treat
the Queen's uniform.
You're English?
Who are you?
My name is Alexander MacLennan,
I work for José Menéndez.
You know that name?
Menéndez?
No.
He is the owner of these lands.
You look worn, soldier.
Join us at our camp.
We appreciate the invitation,
but we still have a long journey
ahead of us,
we should resist
keeping our employers waiting.
First you must wash that tunic.
We appreciate the invitation...
Are you going to turn down
my hospitality?
What silliness!
Of course you'll join us.
I'm not used to being rebuffed.
Here.
Have a drink, Lieutenant.
It's a private's uniform.
Not a lieutenant's.
Private?
I can't fucking believe it!
You son of a bitch!
When did you serve?
In the '80s.
Transvaal? Egypt?
Yes.
Regiment?
In the 75th as a rifleman.
Gordon Highlanders.
Tel El Kebir?
- Yes.
- Lucky you.
And yourself?
Royal Scots, First Battalion.
Lydenburg and Bermondsey.
You would have served
under Colonel Martin.
Close...
You are Colonel Martin!
I was, until bad fortune
brought me here.
It's an honor
to be at your table, Colonel.
Indeed it is.
It's an honor for me
to meet a Colonel
who has no problem with
a private sitting at the same table!
Cause that just ain't normal,
ain't it?
We are at the ends
of the Earth, mate.
Things are more relaxed.
You and your men
should rest here for the night,
and continue in the morning.
That's a generous offer, Colonel,
but my orders were very specific.
And you, my friend?
Would you stay?
I don't know, maybe.
That all depends, Colonel.
Stay and do what, exactly?
Pursue our cravings.
I do like the sound of that!
Good boy.
I've been following orders
from this English red pig
for I don't know how many days now!
It'd be pleasure to spend
some time with a real officer
and a proper Englishman
like yourself!
Excellent news!
You should choose your men
more wisely, soldier.
- He referred to you as English.
- Yes, and what of it?
You're a Scot!
Have some self-respect!
I have no time for traitors.
Less so if they're from
the old colonies.
I have my orders, Colonel,
you understand?
Yes.
Kiepja!
Come here!
I said, come here!
Come, sit with us.
Kiepja...
Do you like this man?
No, don't like.
Aren't these natives
extraordinary?
Do you want her?
Kiepja...
these men are interested in you.
Would you like to go with them?
They're good men.
Like myself.
I'm sorry you lost a man, soldier.
Take the squaw.
She'll be of more use to you
than the American.
Me and my men,
we don't really fancy the natives.
I suppose my tastes
are a little more refined.
Do you understand?
It seems like a fair trade.
But there is one more detail...
You are sad.
Here is bad.
Men hit me.
Koliot hit me. Don't like.
You're not white.
It's for you.
For hunt, for cook,
like a knife.
I make it.
Don't like these men.
Me horse with you.
PUNTA ARENAS, CHILE
7 YEARS LATER
THE RED PIG
Have we heard from our guest?
He wanted to stop by his hotel
to bathe before coming.
Why does he need a hotel?
Does he think
we don't have hot water?
Presidents have stayed in this house.
I find it utterly rude.
What do we know of this man?
He is an intellectual.
Apparently,
a nationalist.
Mr. Vicuña is here.
I'm very sorry for the delay.
Madam, a pleasure.
Monsignor, a pleasure.
I'm sorry I missed the ceremony
at the square this morning.
I was taken by surprise.
Don José,
it's a pleasure to be in your home.
Welcome.
We were waiting for you.
Please have a seat.
Thank you.
Margarita,
please serve him some tea.
What brings you to these lands,
Mr. Vicuña?
We plan to celebrate
the first 100 years of our nation.
And we want to do more
than opening new parks,
libraries or museums.
The President of the Republic
asked me to visit
the farthest regions of our country,
to learn and understand
the needs of our people.
The men who come from the capital
quickly leave these lands,
leaving behind...
nothing more than infamy.
"Desolation Island".
"Port Hunger",
"Useless Bay".
I hope you are not one of them.
It's as if those infamous names
not only speak
of our rough geography,
but also of the terrible crimes
committed here.
What crimes?
Have you heard
of Alexander MacLennan?
Of course.
He worked many years for me.
Unfortunately,
he is no longer in this world.
As I recall,
the newspaper "La Razón"
wrote a long article about him
a few years ago.
Somewhat of a...
gruesome story.
Hard to believe.
It is said MacLennan and other men
poisoned the almost 200 tons of meat
of a whale stranded on the beach,
ending the lives
of almost 100 Indians
who ate it.
I don't read the local press.
Apparently, MacLennan,
nicknamed the Red Pig,
hunted Indians across the pampas.
What a fascination for tabloids!
Out of respect,
we should call him
Lieutenant MacLennan.
Not "Red Pig"?
- No.
- Why not?
Because he did not like it.
They called him that
out of pure envy.
Envy is a difficult sin to fight.
The human being is so complex
and so fragile at the same time.
That is also where his value lies.
In his ability to choose, to fail,
but also to forgive and be forgiven.
The Indians could resist the cold,
even naked,
but our illnesses killed them,
even God couldn't help them.
We know, Monsignor.
We know all we've done
for the Indians.
With your narrow city mind,
you can't imagine
all the food we gave them.
Nor all the orphans
taken into decent homes.
Are you referring
to the auction of Indians
that took place in the
square of Punta Arenas?
What you read in the capital
are not newspapers, but satires!
Those satires
accuse you of paying a pound
for each severed Ona ear
and almost two pounds
for a woman's uterus.
You come here, to our home,
and make accusations
as if we were delinquents.
We've killed many savages
and will continue, if necessary.
You are busy
with politics in the north,
while we are working!
My father gets older
on each business trip
to promote land development.
Thanks to our effort
and to those dead Indians,
you are here,
in the last corner of the Earth.
In this "inhospitable",
"untamable" place,
we provided food
for thousands of children
roaming around the dirty streets
of your capital!
I am sorry.
Here, we can talk seriously,
Mr. Vicuña.
I thought we were talking seriously.
No, that was politics.
Politics aren't serious?
I don't think so.
Especially when led by men
who don't know their country.
Our goal is the creation
of a new nation,
made by Chileans,
settlers and Indians.
Together we must build
this beautiful country.
For this, peace is necessary.
Here, we live in peace...
We have an agreement
with the Mapuche.
No agreements are made
with the Indians.
They neither respect the Law
nor their word.
But we must respect ours.
What do you need?
I want to meet the Onas.
Listen to them.
Talk to them.
The Onas don't speak!
Maybe not with you.
They never interested me much...
Maybe this might interest you:
we must renew the agreement
you signed 10 years ago
to manage these lands.
Lands that have gained much value,
about 15 times
the price you paid for them.
And as you know,
the ratification of the agreement
depends on our Congress,
and not on our friend,
President Pedro Montt.
I want you to keep
the administration of these lands.
Thank you, Mr. Vicuña.
It seems...
only fair to me.
But as I was saying,
the stories that reach Santiago,
instead of helping, make it harder
to convince the deputies.
I know you're very proud
of your achievements,
but we,
as children of this young
and noble motherland,
must take care of the optics.
We are interested in aesthetics.
What aesthetics?
Wool stained with blood
loses all value.
What do you want?
CHILOÉ ISLAND, CHILE
Good afternoon, madam.
Does Mr. Segundo Molina live here?
Laura, read!
Segundo Molina:
Camino del Rosal,
Town of Tenaun,
department of Dalcahue,
Chiloé Island,
Republic of Chile.
Is that here?
It is here.
Where is he?
He is off to sea.
Are you his wife?
Yes. And who are you?
Marcial Vicuña.
I work for the President.
What president?
The President of Chile, Pedro Montt.
Never heard of him.
We must talk with Mr. Segundo.
Don José Menéndez
said he could help us.
Help you with what?
Do you know who José Menéndez is?
No.
When is your husband coming back?
I don't know.
When men leave,
one never knows if they will be back.
What is your name, Madam?
Rosa.
Let's make a deal, Rosa. Shall we?
I propose
that you invite me in,
so we can talk quietly.
If you accept,
I won't tell these police officers
that you are hiding something.
Are you going to arrest him?
Why would we?
Do you accept?
I thank you,
deeply, for inviting me
into your home.
Do you mind
if my assistant joins us?
No.
Laura, come.
I don't work
for those people anymore.
But you did work there.
Yes, many years ago.
They say the things
that happened there
were terrible.
That many Indians died.
We want to report
those awful crimes.
Why are you so interested?
- To do justice.
- Justice?
That's why I need to talk to you,
Segundo.
About what?
An interview.
What do you want to know?
What jobs did you do
for José Menéndez?
I worked with the sheep,
herding them,
shearing them in the sheds.
With my dogs,
we moved thousands of sheep.
And now, what do you do?
I have my animals,
my boat.
We live off the sea.
But do you earn money?
We live off
what the sea gives us.
How?
The sea is wise.
If you respect it,
it takes care of you.
It'd be very important for me
to have an image of you.
An image?
An image...
that gives truth
to your testimony.
A portrait.
Photographs,
but in motion...
Rosa, may I ask you a question?
What?
How did you two meet?
Once,
along with the Lieutenant...
- What lieutenant?
- Lieutenant MacLennan.
Things were complicated
and Menéndez wanted
no more problems with the Indians.
So, the Lieutenant became Judge.
Judge?
A Peace Judge, said Menéndez.
We had to talk to the Indians
and make peace.
Rosa helped us communicate.
We spent months touring the island,
talking to them.
Once,
the Lieutenant had the idea
to offer a meal.
He organized a banquet on a beach.
A lot of Indians arrived,
there must have been 300 of them.
We had roasted lambs,
more than 50 animals
on the spit.
The Indians ate and drank
all they wanted.
They got to the meat
and tore it apart with their teeth,
as if they had never eaten.
Then we brought the wine
in large pots.
When the sun set,
many were already drunk,
lying on the sand.
Then we took the rifles
and started shooting.
The Indians began to run.
They went into the sea.
We chased them
and strangled them with our hands
until they stopped moving.
The sea turned red.
You must have been
through very hard times.
But I assure you that your sacrifices
and your wife's
have not been in vain.
Segundo, are you alright?
Yes?
The hat does not bother you?
Perfect! Very good!
Laura, fill the cup of tea please,
will you?
All good there?
Yes? Is the focus alright?
Fix her blouse.
Please.
The other side also.
And the hair there, right there.
Nice.
Very good.
Very good. Let's start.
Let's shoot.
Have some tea.
Rosa?
Can you take your cup?
Rosa!
The cup.
In your hand,
at the level of your face, please.
Rosa please.
Could you stir your cup of tea?
Rosa, do you want
to be part of this nation?
Drink the tea.